Today's דף *Daf* is פ *Pei* 80 and we pick up on
the משנה Mishna *Mishna* on the bottom of ע"ט עמוד ב' *Ayin
Tes Amud Beis* and the משנה Mishna *Mishna* reads as follows. So
we've been dealing with a long משנה Mishna *Mishna*, probably at least
two משניות *Mishnayos* stuck together. So until now, of course, we've been
dealing with the act of giving the גט get *Get* and the
woman, what's defined as the woman's domain, the man's domain, the act
of giving, how much I've been raising the question all along, does
it parallel definitions by קנינים *Kinyanim* or does it have other definitions,
huge amount of discussion in the ראשונים *Rishonim* which you didn't see
necessarily reflected in the דף *Daf*. Anyway, and now we're moving sort
of to other to we we've totally have switched gears, I don't
know if you realized it, but that quick little משנה mishnah *Mishna*
yesterday about using an old גט get *Get*, a גט get. *Get*
that existed after ייחוד *Yichud*, and is that a problem or not,
now that had nothing to do with the act of giving the
גט get *Get*. So now we're sort of dealing with possible problems,
other types of possible פסולים psulim. *Psulim* or problems in a גט
get *Get*. Okay, so with that in mind, let's take a look
at the משנה mishnah *Mishna*. כתב לשום מלכות malchus שאינה הוגנת *Kasav
lishum malchus she'eino hogenet*. If the גט get, *Get* was written in
the name of an improper government. Now that the גמרא Gemara *Gemorah*
is going to say it means specifically it was dated by Roman
dating, by the dating of the Roman Caesar, and we'll see why
the גמרא Gemara *Gemorah* calls that an improper government
even if you have the right year but by then...
Right, you gave the third year of the Caesar Hadrian or whatever,
that's a problem because now you could say that that's even if
you're under Roman control, which is presumably what actually was the case
for the authors of the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*, that they were under
Roman control. And so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemorah* is going to frame
it, I mean at least the way sort of רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
frames it, but it sounds like this from the גמרא Gemara *Gemorah*,
that the problem is that you're dating by a government that is
not your government, that is not your authority. So, and therefore
it's a problem because there's like a שלום מלכות shlom malchus? *Shalom
Malchus* problem, that they wanted you to give a date for your
גט get *Get*, and actually we're going to see in a minute,
not even based on Jewish dating, they wanted you to date your
גט get *Get* based on the dating of the country in which
the גט get *Get* was being written. So that was like motivated
by שלום מלכות shalom malchut *Shalom Malchus*, but interestingly, that's even a
בדיעבד bediavad *Bedi'eved* problem. But again, the question, the historical question is,
what does it mean if that's the פשט pshat *Pshat* in the
משנה Mishna, *Mishna*, which is not clear. מלכות malchut שאינה הוגנת *Malchus
she'eino hogenet* might mean something else, but the way the גמרא Gemara
*Gemorah* understands it, that it means Rome, I mean what's the problem?
The משנה Mishna. *Mishna* was being written in Roman Palestine, the Jews
were under Roman,
under Rome. So it's not clear that the problem in the משנה
Mishnah *Mishna* that that's פשט *Pshat* in the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*. I
can't understand historically how that could be פשט *Pshat*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*,
did you want to say something, Charlie?
Oh, I looked to have something mentioned after.
Okay, so I just
want to understand what you're saying. So let's say I'm in America
and then I'm saying like, you know, based on the Roman Caesar
and there's no Rome in America, that would be the problem? Yes.
Now what if it's Rome doing another Roman thing, that would be
okay?
That is the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemorah* understood it. I'm not
telling you that that's פשט *Pshat* in that line מלכות malchut שאינה
הוגנת *Malchus she'eino hogenet*. Right, מלכות malchut שאינה הוגנת *Malchus she'eino hogenet*
could be read as, I don't know, you know, you right now
are some like some little upstart government that's not a real government,
and you're
Correct,
it would be definitely the problem. Daddy daddy declares his house to
be...
Okay, so anyway, so you could imagine something like that, right? But
anyway, but that's not how the גמרא Gemara, *Gemorah*'s going to explain
it. The גמרא Gemara *Gemorah*'s going to explain it means that it's
based some dating that is not the dating in your country that
is not showing proper sort of respect and subservience and acknowledgment of
the kingship or, you know, of the government under which you are
living. All right, so anyway, we'll see more of that. But again,
I don't know historically how that makes any sense since they were
living under Rome. Okay. Anyway, לשום מלכות malchut מדי, לשום מלכות malchut.
יון *Lishum malchus Madai, lishum malchus Yavan*. Now let's say you date
this is just again some other government. You do it
by the kingdom of the Medians or of the Greeks. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemorah* no, that's presumably a different issue. Now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemorah* is going to say that the point is that that's
like a dead country, dead dating. You know, this is like since
370 years since King דריוש *Daryavesh* of Persia. So he's dead, so
maybe nobody cares about that, it's no longer a competing
government, it's no longer a competing מלכות malchut *Malchus*. So that's the
way the גמרא Gemara *Gemorah* is going to understand that that's a
חידוש chiddush *Chiddush*, that it's not only if you name it after
a government after a מלכות malchut. *Malchus* that isn't yours that exists
right now in the world, but even if you name it after
a long dead מלכות malchut *Malchus*, it's still going to be a
problem. One minute. Again, there's other ways you could have read this
משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, of course, that the problem is not just it's
a competing one, but there's some other problems here. Anyway, but look,
even if it's a good Jewish dating, ובבנין הבית, ובחורבן הבית *U’v’vinyan
habayis, u’v’churban habayis*. If you date it from the time of the
building of the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash *Beis Hamikdash* or the destruction
of the בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash? *Beis Hamikdash*, all of those are
no good according to the גמרא Gemara *Gemorah*. and the תוספות Tosfos
is going to ask and we'll get to: so how is it
that we date our גיטין gittin לבריאת העולם, L'vrias Haolam, right? Why
don't we date our גיטין gittin ממניין המלכות? Miminyan HaMalchus? So תוספות
Tosfos is going to ask that. But what's clear at least from
the end of the משנה Mishnah is that the problem is not
that somehow it's intrinsically bad to be dating something that way. Like
you can't say it's intrinsically bad to be dating something from בניין
בית המקדש Binyan Beis HaMikdash or חורבן בית המקדש, Churban Beis HaMikdash,
right? So it sounds so clearly there's some sense that in this
context it was the wrong thing to be doing and that's how
the גמרא Gemara understands it. The consistent problem in the משנה Mishnah
is you're supposed to be giving it the dating based on the
country and the government under which you currently live. Yes, Charlie.
מלכות יוון Malchus Yavan is the chronology that is in First Maccabees,
and that calendar was actually used throughout the Middle East through the
Middle Ages by Christians. Right, so this is a חידוש that they
can't use a commonly used calendar.
Right, that's a very good point, and that's also I think something
called I think that's מניין שטרות Minyan Shtaros if I remember correctly.
There was something called מניין שטרות Minyan Shtaros which was a widespread
dating system which went back to some type of a Greek event,
was it when the Greeks were victorious over the Persians or something?
It was the beginning of the Seleucid monarchy.
Oh was it?
Okay. So which was what we thought... It was one of Alexander's
successors.
Right. 311 BC. And I believe that that's מניין שטרות. Minyan Shtaros.
So so it's very interesting, right? The classic datings that are known
that were in Jewish documents, number one מניין שטרות, Minyan Shtaros, which
was presumably what's meant by מלכות יוון; Malchus Yavan; or בניין הבית
Binyan HaBayis or חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayis, okay, and those would not
be good. So it's clearly there's not an intrinsic problem here, probably
has something to do as the גמרא Gemara is going to understand
it that it is the, that you have to give fealty or
respect to the government under which you're living. Yes?
Does תוספות Tosfos mean that you might be inclined to use something
that's, so to speak, a dead language for culturally nostalgic reasons?
What תוספות Tosfos you talking about?
הכתב לשם מלכות שאינה הוגנת? Hakstav l'shem malchus she'einah hogenes? Is it
called that because it just...
No, no, we'll see that in the גמרא. Gemara Let's not worry
about that now. Okay. גמרא Gemara. says like this: היה במזרח וכתב
במערב, במערב וכתב במזרח. Haya b'mizrach v'chasav b'ma'arav, b'ma'arav v'chasav b'mizrach. So
that's one set of problems. It's the correct date but but you
know, not the the system we want you to use. Now 'it'
used, which the גמרא Gemara is going to say means the סופר
sofer and the עדים, edim, were in the east of the city.
They were in East Berlin, okay, and they wrote in West Berlin.
Okay, they wrote, they wrote: 'We were in West Berlin, you know,
in West Berlin on this
day, etc.' Like you know how a כתובה kesubah starts, באחד בשבת
B'echad b'shabbos whatever, במניין שאנו מונים, biminyan she'anu monim, you know, כאן,
kan, New York, New York, you know, right, like Los Angeles, whatever.
Anyway, so they wrote במניין שאנו מונים, biminyan she'anu monim, right, you
know, whatever, West Berlin, and they were in East Berlin, okay. So
היה במזרח וכתב במערב, וכתב במזרח. Haya b'mizrach v'chasav b'ma'arav, v'chasav b'mizrach.
תצא. Teizei. So that's also invalid, that they gave the wrong place
where they were located when the גט get was being written. In
those cases, wrong dating or wrong location, okay, what's the הלכה? halacha?
Very, very strict set of rules. So this is going to now
say what happens when you have a גט get that is בטל,
batel, but it's בטל batel really מדרבנן. miderabbanan.
It's very strange רש״י. Rashi. רש״י Rashi sounds like it's a that
it's בטל מדאורייתא, batel mide'oraisa, but nevertheless it's like we treat it
as though it's still good מדרבנן, miderabbanan, but that's not פשט at
all. How could these problems be דאורייתא de'oraisa problems? Especially, right, right,
right, well that's going to be what it's going to be like.
Anyway, especially this thing about like just the dating is based on
שלום מלכות? shalom malchut So I can't explain רש״י. Rashi. תוספות Tosafot.
says that it's all cases of בטל מדרבנן. batel miderabbanan. But look,
you know, there's an interesting question and the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask this. Is every case of a problem, of a פסול,
psul, a case that's going to have severe consequences like this? Like
a minute ago we talked about a גט ישן, get yashan, where
we said that בדיעבד if it was given you could get married
or if you get married you don't have to get divorced. So
presumably there are degrees of פסולים. And this משנה Mishnah is identifying
the גיטין gittin that are as sort of as, you know, as
like the biggest
problem, okay, but actually
it's only a דרבנן derabbanan problem, okay, which means that מדאורייתא mide'oraisa
she's married, but in a very weighty way מדרבנן miderabbanan we consider
her to be not married, which means that's going to... right, which
means it's going to be the worst of both worlds. Right? You
understand? Okay. So מדאורייתא mide'oraisa she's married, but מדרבנן miderabbanan it's such
a big problem, we've identified this as a category of a big
problem, that מדרבנן miderabbanan we're going to look at it like she
is בכלל bechlal not married, and מדאורייתא mide'oraisa she בכלל bechlal is
married, and then of course it's going to be disastrous. Okay. Now
the גמרא, Gemara I'm just going to ruin the surprise because you're
all going to get upset when you hear the list of consequences
of this. Okay, and especially these would not be the ones I
would put at the top of my list of things that would
be the worst types of problems. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is
going to say that this is following the position of רבי מאיר,
Rebbi Meir, and רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says: כל המשנה ממטבע שטבעו
חכמים בגיטין הולד
ממזר. Kol hamishaneh mimatbeia shetavu chachamim begittin havlad mamzer. יוציא והולד ממזר.
Yotzi v'havlad mamzer. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is like very... very, very
demanding about everything has to be exactly the נוסח nusach and the
way we did it, and anybody who changes and varies, she has
to get divorced and we treat the kid as a ממזר mamzer
and all those types of things, even if דאורייתא de'oraita it's still
a good גט. get, Now again, did רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir put
everything in that category? Not clear, but at least at least the
things we're going to be looking at and things that were considered
about and maybe, you know, because also this is a question, right?
It's like changing from
ממטבע שתבעו חכמים. mimatbei'ah shetavu chachamim. I want us at least to
pay attention to that, you know, it's like this type of phrase
comes up now when people want to make some changes in דאוונינג.
davening. You know, it's like it's like they gave you a particular
text, a particular formulation. You have got to don't vary from that
text. So other problems like גט ישן get yashan or I don't
know, you had only כתב סופר ועד, ksav sofer ve'ed, other types
of types of issues that came up, you did the right text.
Here the problem was you did not use the right text. Now
some of that text is variable. We don't know where the סופר
sofer is going to be. We don't know what מלכות Malchut, you're
going to be under, but we have very precise rules about how
the text is to be written. So that seems to be at
least the locus of these problems. You're switching the text, we're מקפיד
makpid on the text, and therefore it's going to be very consequential.
So let's see what the consequence is. One minute, let's see what
the consequence is, okay? So תצא מזה ומזה. tetzei mizeh umizeh. She
has to get divorced from if she married a second guy, but
she can't go back to her first husband, because we basically treat
it as why get divorced from the second guy because we're going
to treat it like you were still married, okay? So if you
were still married, you can't stay with the second guy. But you
need a גט get from him. Why do you need a גט
get, from him? Because we're going to treat it like the גט,
get, the first גט get was good and you were married to
the guy. So you have to leave the guy, but you need
a גט get from him. Okay, and she's with the first guy?
And she can't go back to the first guy because if you
were still married, then the first guy, then you were committing adultery,
and therefore you can't go back to your current husband, so you
have to not be with your current husband. But, you know, you're
going to need a גט get from your current husband, okay? So
you need a גט get. from both of the men, because, you
know, we sort of treat her in both categories, וצריכה גט מזה
ומזה, u'tzrichah get mizeh umizeh, so she just, so she has to
leave both men, she needs a גט get, from both men, ואין
לה, ve'ein lah, and she doesn't, she's not entitled from either of
the husbands, right? לא כתובה, lo kesubah, she doesn't get her כתובה
kesubah payment of 200 זוז. zuz. Now, she's really the one who
suffers as a result of this, even though she did nothing wrong.
רש"י Rashi tries to explain, again based on the גמרא Gemara in
יבמות Yevamos and so on, that like, oh, this is a fine
for her because she should have been more careful, which is like
what? Like why are we expecting her? He was the one that
wrote it. Women, men were the more literate ones in society anyway.
He was the one, I mean she was the innocent person that
just passively receiving the גט, get. right? So I don't begin to
understand how anybody, I mean רש"י Rashi explains it this way, but
I don't I don't really begin to understand how we could sort
of see this like she's being punished for doing something wrong. Maybe
this comes up in יבמות, Yevamos, because in יבמות Yevamos the issue
is she got a report that her husband was dead based on
an עד אחד ed echad and she went and she remarried and
then the husband shows up alive, and then it has the same
set of series of consequences. So there you could say we're going
to punish her seriously so she's going to be very careful before
she gets remarried. But that's not really relevant here, and it just
seems like חז"ל Chazal are just like saying like, I the only
way I see that understood is that it's not an issue of
a punishment, it's just, look, we just have to deal with the
consequences. The consequences were that she's married to the first guy and
married to the second guy, and, you know, what would be the
relevant consequences of that reality? And that reality is how could she
get a כתובה kesubah from, you know, from somebody if from one
lens of looking at it she's committing adultery, you know, with the
other person? How she could get a how could she get a
כתובה kesubah from guy number two if she was never married to
guy number two? And she can't get a כתובה kesubah from guy
number one because now she was committing adultery with guy number two.
So, you know, so it's not fair, okay, but I'd rather look
at it as a not fair and just a unfortunate consequence of
her status than look at it as a conscious punishing her for
something I can't understand how she could be punished for.
So let's say she didn't get married to the second guy?
So the גמרא Gemara is going to deal with that. Let's say
she just, I don't know, slept with somebody, but didn't get married
to them, okay? So the גמרא Gemara is actually going to say
that that could be different, actually, interesting.
And especially if she didn't sleep with anyone, he just gives her
this bad גט get, and like, oh, oh, I get to give
you...
Exactly, exactly. Hold your question, I just want to read the list
of consequences here, okay. וצריכה גט מזה ומזה. u'tzrichah get mizeh umizeh.
ואין לה לא כתובה, ve'ein lah lo kesubah, so she doesn't collect
כתובה kesubah from anybody, ולא פירות, velo peiros, she doesn't, now the
פירות peiros is interesting because פירות peiros is something that he got,
he would be getting her פירות, peiros, and now that they're getting
divorced, of course he doesn't get פירות. peiros. So רש"י Rashi, says
it means what she would get in exchange for the פירות. peiros.
It's a question exactly what פירות peiros means. ולא מזונות, velo mezonos,
she's not does not get, meaning while she's I guess awaiting her
גט, get, she's not getting מזונות mezonos from either party. Again, you
could look at it as a punishment or you could just look
at it as the fact that, well, which guy's she married to?
She's married to two guys, so which guy's the one that's חייב
chayav in מזונות? mezonos? So neither of them have to give her
מזונות, mezonos, okay, but you could also look at it by the
way, and this is interesting, if you don't want to look at
it just as that she's being the one
It could be, right, it could be that he doesn't get פירות,
peirot, right, because maybe the first guy doesn't get פירות peirot because
she's married to the second, second guy doesn't get פירות peirot because
she's married to the first. I don't know, anyway, but sounds like
this is all about what she's suffering. Okay, ולא בלאות, v'lo bl'ot,
she doesn't get her like worn out clothing, okay, when she's sort
of leaving and getting the גט, get. it's seen as like that's
like, you know, she can't get it, like Tosafot reads it, reimbursed
for, you know, clothing that she brought into the marriage and that
now is, has to get thrown out.
לא מזה ולא מזה, lo mizeh v'lo mizeh, she can't get it
from either husband. And אם נטלה מזה ומזה תחזיר, im nitla mizeh
u'mizeh tachzir, if she actually was given it, it's not just a
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah type of a case,
okay, she actually has to even give it back even if she's
in possession of it, which is pretty interesting. Right? So it's, so
again, it's, it does sound a little bit like she's being punished
because even if you define it like somehow she's like ספק safek
married to each guy, married to both guys, like, so why would
you say... like why would she have to give it back if
then there was one lens to look at it like she is
still, so it's not clear.
והולד ממזר מזה ומזה, v'havalad mamzer mizeh u'mizeh, and the child from
either husband is considered a ממזר. mamzer. The second guy 'cause she's
considered first married to the first, and the first guy 'cause she's
considered if she were to go back to him, considered still married
to the second. ולא זה וזה מטמאים לה, v'lo zeh v'zeh mitam'im
lah, she became, if she died, neither of... and they were כהנים,
kohanim, they would not have to become, they would not become טמא
tamei to her to bury her.
Though the second guy can't be a כהן kohen 'cause...
that's
a good point, point. ולא זה וזה זכאים לא במציאתה. v'lo zeh
v'zeh zaka'im lo bimtziatah. Now here we actually get a way that
the husband loses out. They're not entitled to her found objects ולא
במעשה ידיה v'lo b'ma'aseh yadeha or her labor ולא בהפרת נדריה, v'lo
b'hafarat nedareha, they can't,
you know, annul her vows. So, הייתה... haytah... so nobody has any
rights on one another, but of course she's still married to both
of them essentially and needs
a גט get. from both. הייתה בת ישראל, Haytah bat Yisrael, if
she was a בת ישראל, bat Yisrael, נפסלה מן הכהונה, nifselah min
hakehunah, then she now cannot marry a כהן kohen because even I
guess the point is, well I mean... yeah I guess the point
is like if both of them die maybe or whatever. It is
a funny נפסלה מן הכהונה nifselah min hakehunah because anyway since the
first גט get. was really good, she already is a גרושה. gerushah.
Anyway, the point is she's considered now like a זונה zonah because
she slept with a man who wasn't her husband when she's still
married to her husband. But it's a good point, she's a גרושה
gerushah anyway. Anyway, בת לוי מן המעשר, Bat Levi min hama'aser, בת
לוי Bat Levi doesn't get מעשר, ma'aser, which is interesting, since when
מעשר ma'aser doesn't even have קידושין, kiddushin, and since when does, you
know, does somebody lose their ability to eat מעשר? ma'aser? Anyway, that's
discussed in the גמרא ביבמות. Gemara b'Yevamot. בת כהן, Bat Kohen, if
she was a... מן התרומה, min hatrumah, that makes sense, right? She
can't eat תרומה trumah because again, it's considered like she committed adultery
and therefore...
and if she goes back, she has no kids go back to
her father's house, right? Everything ends...
No, because a woman who committed adultery, the same way we say
אחד לבעל ואחד לבועל, echad l'ba'al v'echad l'bo'el, it says ונטמאה v'nitma'ah
three times so she's נפסלה מן הכהונה. nifselah min hakehunah. So it's
not just even if she whatever goes back to her father's house
and has no kids, okay, it's like a פגם, pegam, and she
can't eat... she's excluded from תרומה. trumah. ואין יורשים של זה ויורשים
של זה יורשים כתובתה. v'ein yorshim shel zeh v'yorshim shel zeh yorshim
ktuvatah. Children from either husband don't inherit her כתובה. ktubah. What does
this mean? It means that a woman brings in her dowry, okay?
She goes ahead and she brings in
her... and her dowry is the stuff that basically... so she's got
whatever it is, she's got, you know, these ten fields that are
hers. Now, normal case, I'm this woman's father, and I want to
give her a nice dowry, but if she gets divorced, she'll take
it back out with her. But if she doesn't get divorced, it's
going to, and she dies first, it'll pass on to my grandkids,
right? To her husband and then my grandkids. The only thing is,
let's say her husband marries other women during, after, before. So that
dowry that I've just given my daughter is not just going to
go to my grandkids, it's going to go to all this man's
children. So the כתובה ktubah basically entitles her, this is כתובת בנין
דכרין, ktuvat benin dichrin, that the dowry that she brings into the
marriage passes on only to her children, does not pass down to
the other children, okay? So if she dies first, the husband gets
it, but when the husband dies, it passes down just to her
children, not to all of the husband's heirs, the property that she
brought into the marriage. In this case, okay, that's not true. If
she dies while before she's gotten the גט get from them, okay,
and she brought money in to both estates by the way, because,
you know, she got married to the second guy, she maybe brought
a dowry in to the second guy. She dies, both husbands inherit
her, but then they die, the property does not pass down to
her children, it passes down equally to all the kids. And you're
going to ask, what?
You'll ask it in a minute. Of course the problem is like,
so why does her husband inherit her? Like again, so many of
these things does seem not just like I wanted to frame it
like it's a natural consequence of having this double definition, but like
why does her husband inherit her? Why don't we say, well, she's
doubtfully married to either, maybe neither of them should inherit her? So
it's discussed in the... Sounds less that she's like doubtfully married to
either and it sounds more that she's definitely married to both, some
type of a status of that nature, okay? But you know, again,
like some of them, if she's definitely married to both, let her
get her כתובה. kesuvah. So it's like, it does seem like she's
you know, constantly suffering here and getting the short end of the
stick.
Wait, she doesn't have a כתובה? kesuvah? So what's the point of
saying this?
No, no, no. Her not having her כתובה kesuvah means she doesn't
take out the two hundred זוז zuz when she gets her גט.
get Now, it might also mean she doesn't take out her dowry
when she gets a גט, get, but does... no, because normally if
a woman is divorced, let's say, for cause, she doesn't get her
two hundred זוז, zuz, she doesn't get her תוספת, tosefet, but she
does take out the property she brought in. Okay? So when she
says don't get כתובה, kesuvah, it doesn't mean she doesn't take out
her dowry. Okay, but when she dies, okay, but we're not talking
about that she got the גט. get Before she got the גט,
get, she died. So her husband inherited her. And her husband took
the property she brought in and now that property will pass down
equally to the kids, not just to her kids. But again, like
why is that fair that her husband inherits her and but she
doesn't you know? So it does seem like she's very much the
one suffering from all of this.
What?
It sounds like she is. Yeah, I know, I know.
It's very hard to understand why she suffers so much. Okay, and
then one more line: ואם
מת אחיו של זה ואחיו של זה חולצין ולא מיבמין. V'im meis
achiv shel zeh v'achiv shel zeh choltzin v'lo meyabmin. If the husbands
died before giving a גט, get then their brothers have to do
חליצה chalitzah not יבום. yibbum.
Before giving her a new גט. get.
Before giving her a new גט. get. Well, the first guy before
a new גט. get Then the brothers have to do חליצה chalitzah
not יבום yibbum because again she's considered to be ספק safek married
to each guy, so you can't do יבום, yibbum, but she might
not be married so you have to do חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, there
were some questions. Zev, you had a question? No. Charlie, you had
a question?
This proves that women need to learn Talmud.
Okay, yes.
My question is a little bit different because I find it interesting
is you know, I hear some people that say like, you know,
you can't date like whatever it is, 2016, but here clearly we're
dating kings' times. Or is it maybe 2016 would be a problem
because that's after like a particular religion and whereas dating days of
kings is different? I don't know, I'm just asking the question. Like,
could this...
so we'll see that. We'll get to תוספות. Tosafot He's going to
discuss our contemporary practice. Okay, yes?
So the ממזרים, mamzerim, it's a little bit... is that if she
ends up going back to the first husband? It doesn't retroactively...
Correct, not retroactively. Only any children for for the ממזר mamzer from
the first husband if she goes back to him. From the second
guy, though, it's kids she's already had because we're saying she's still
married to the first guy and whatever.
But how would she end up going back to the first...?
She's not listening! You tell me that the גט get wasn't good?
I gotta leave this guy and go back... whatever. I mean, but
you're right, but that's very important to clarify. It's only the ממזר
mamzer from the first husband is only kids after she's been with
the second guy. Okay, after she was married to the second guy.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Like because if
a woman just commits adultery, just, whatever, and then goes back to
her first husband, the kid's not ממזרים. mamzeirim. The only way we
would conceptualize, right, the kids being ממזרים mamzeirim is if she was
married to the second guy. So what we're going to say is,
you know, if you go back to, like that's important, right, if
you go back to the first husband without getting a גט get
from the second husband is really what we're saying, right, then the
kids are ממזרים. mamzeirim. Even if she would go back after getting
the גט, get right, the kids wouldn't be ממזרים. mamzeirim. So it's
only a ממזר mamzer if they were born afterwards.
Correct. Correct. But you can't. But he can't.
You can't, but if you did. Okay, but that's very important to
clarify. Correct. The ממזר ממזרים mamzer mamzeirim from the first husband is
only if she went back to the first husband without a גט
get. from the second.
Okay, all right, but then fully understand even if the second husband
does give a גט, get? she still can't go back to the
first.
Yeah, yeah, she's not allowed to, but if she did. Okay. But
the ממזר mamzer from the second husband is any kids she has
from the second husband
because she was technically, right, technically, right, she was... we're considering it
as if she was still married to the first husband.
That's what
seemed to you...
Yes, I mean, the question is, as if... Yeah, but the question
is, I'm not sure that if we consider her married to two
people, all of these consequences make sense. So that's... some of it
is because we're considering her ספק safek married, some because we're considering
her married to both. But yes, that's part of the point. This
גט get is both בטל batel and not בטל batel at the
same time. So she's both married and not married to the second
guy and married and not married to the first guy. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara, says like this: שינה שמו ושמה שמו ושמה.
Shina shemo u'shmah shemo u'shemah. Now here's a second scenario, again, where
it's a textual change in the גט. get If you change the
name of the husband or the wife,
and by the way, this doesn't mean really changed it, you know,
you wrote Steve instead of Fred because that obviously... that would be
like obviously פסול. pasul. We're talking here about a Rabbinic problem. Or,
right, you wrote Steve... even? Yeah, you didn't do... right. תוספות Tosafot
says, you know, לא
שינה ממש, lo shina mamash, תוספות Tosafot says, וכן שינה עירו v'chen
sheni iro means you wrote some name that was a little bit
imprecise or whatever, I forget the earlier גמרא Gemara? yet, let's take
a look.
Okay, ל"ד עמוד ב', Lamed Dalet Amud Bet, the גמרא Gemara says
רמיא אפסתא. Ramya Aspata. Let's look there quickly. It says
Yeah, it's like וכל שום שיש לה, vechol shum sheyesh lah, it's
all the other names, right, it's all the nicknames, those types of
things.
You mean he didn't put in all the nicknames?
Yeah, or something like that. Yeah, I mean there's a question, you
don't have to put in all the nicknames, it's worse to do
it wrong than to do it not at all. Anyway you can
go back and look at that גמרא. Gemara. But the point is
you made a change even if it's not a huge substantive change.
Okay? או שמו ושם עירו, o shemo veshem iro, or the wrong
name of the city, but again as תוספות Tosafot says even if
it's not really the fully wrong, it's not like you said Los
Angeles instead of New York. You know, you said some name that
was a little bit off. Okay. תצא מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו
בה. teitzei mizeh umizeh vechol hadrachim ha'elu bah. She has to get
divorced from both and all these consequences apply to her. All right.
So כל העריות שאמרו צרותיהן
מותרות. kol ha'arayot she'amru tzaroteihen mutarot. All of the... now here's another
סוגיא sugya which has nothing to do with a wrong text of
a גט. get כל העריות שאמרו צרותיהן מותרות. kol ha'arayot she'amru tzaroteihen
mutarot. Remember יבום, yibbum, we never get away from יבום. yibbum. So
anytime they say, right, if a brother dies and the surviving brother
and he was married to two wives, and one of those wives
is I don't know, is the surviving brother's whatever, daughter. Okay, so
he can't obviously do יבום yibbum with his daughter. So because she's
an ערווה arvah to him, so because she's an ערווה arvah to
him, so both wives are exempt from יבום yibbum and חליצה chalitzah
and they just walk away, okay?
Guy married his niece?
Yeah. Guy married his niece. So that was the first משנה in
יבמות. Yevamot. Okay, so כל העריות שאמרו צרותיהן מותרות. kol ha'arayot she'amru
tzaroteihen mutarot. So if the case of יבום yibbum one of the
woman is an ערווה arvah to the brother, then their צרות tzarot
therefore are permissible, don't, neither wife needs יבום yibbum or חליצה. chalitzah.
So and what do they do? הלכו הצרות halchu hatzarot so the
co-wives went, האלו ha'elu and ונישאו venisu and they went and they
married other men, reasonable thing. ונמצאו אלו
אילונית. venimtzu elu ailonit. And then what happened was was that the
niece/daughter turned out that once she grew up and it turned out
that she you know never developed sexually whatever, never had... אילונית ailonit
is a... that's just a woman who's barren, it's a woman that
has male characteristics and and therefore the presumption is
that it would have been a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. Okay? If
somebody knows that a woman is an אילונית ailonit and chooses to
marry her, fine. But if he doesn't and she turns out to
be an אילונית, ailonit, the presumption is that it's a מקח טעות.
mekach ta'ut.
He wouldn't have wanted to marry her had he known. So therefore
it's not... nobody was deceiving anybody, it's facts whatever, just now you
know. So the fact is we say, ah, retroactively he was never
married to his niece. So therefore when he died,
she wasn't one of the wives, and therefore the other wife was
obligated in יבום yibbum with the brother. You got it? You got
the scenario?
She should have really done חליצה chalitzah because...
nobody did חליצה. chalitzah. You didn't need חליצה, chalitzah, right? You got
the case? Yeah, I got my pictures over there. I'm going to...
ערווה arvah to an ערווה. arvah.
Ah, that's an interesting point.
Yeah. This is right out of the first משנה in יבמות. Yevamot.
Yep. All right. So here's
ראובן Reuven
and here's שמעון Shimon and שמעון Shimon is married to Ruby, okay?
Okay, so anyway which is which is which is his daughter, right,
okay, and to a woman and to and to דבורה. Dvorah. Okay,
so now he dies. Okay, so in this case, that's my daughter,
so obviously I don't have a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum here,
so I don't have a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum or חליצה
chalitzah with either, they just walk away. So דבורה Dvorah goes ahead
and she marries somebody else. Then Ruby grows up and we find
out that she was a... that she was an אילונית. ailonit. So
now we know, oh, retroactively he was never married to my daughter.
So when he died, there was no ערווה, arvah, I was חייב
chayav to do חליצה chalitzah or יבום yibbum with דבורה. Dvorah. So
דבורה Dvorah now is married to some other man for 20 years,
for 20 years, and it turns out that she should have been,
oops, and it turns out that she was, that she should have
had חליצה chalitzah before she got married to another man. Okay, now
of course like since when is that her fault? All right. Moving
on. Okay, what happens? הלכו צרות אלו ונישאו halchu tzarot elu venisu
ונמצאו אלו אילונית venimtzu elu ailonit תצא מזה ומזה וכל
הדרכים האלו בה. teitzei mizeh umizeh vechol hadrachim ha'elu bah. She gets
all of the consequences.
Now
the big problem here with this is is that is that even
if she was חייבת chayevet in חליצה, chalitzah, right, she was חייבת
chayevet in חליצה, chalitzah, she's not married to this guy, and going
and living with another man, why would that make the kid a
ממזר? mamzer? Why would that you know I mean she's so so
she's lacking חליצה. chalitzah. So a woman she's you know a woman
who's considered זקוקה ליבום zekukah leyibbum and the איסור issur is an
איסור לאו issur lav לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר. lo
tihyeh eishet hamet hachutzah le'ish zar. So she ignored that, she married
some other man without getting חליצה, chalitzah, let's say even willingly, right?
What's why is that so consequential? So the גמרא Gemara basically says
that this is following the גמרא Gemara in יבמות, Yevamot, the position
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says that the child of such
a union is an is a ממזר. mamzer. Now that could be
in general רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva treats the child of a union
with an איסור לאו issur lav as a ממזר, mamzer, but it
also could be specifically about יבום yibbum because you might remember זקוקה
ליבום zekukah leyibbum could be considered to be like
a
quasi-קידושין. kiddushin. she is to some degree quasi-ראובן's Reuven wife, and therefore
she's ראובן's Reuven wife who's now married to somebody else or ראובן's,
Reuven you know, almost wife married to somebody else and has all
of these consequences.
But that's according to if you make it a דעת יחיד, da'at
yachid, a very extreme position.
All right, and the first position was also רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
but yeah, I understand, yeah.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does make all
resulting of לאו lav ממזרים. mamzerim.
Yeah, but there's some question what his original position was. The גמרא
sort of moves, develops it that way, but it's possible his original
statement was a little more limited. But anyway, but yes, but it
could be, it could be רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and it could
even be something a little more specific to ייבום. yibbum.
So just to understand, so according to this then, either the court
would have to wait, you know, however long it is, twenty years
until we figure out whether ראובן Ruby was, you know, whatever, an
אילונית aylonit or not? Or, or just we just get ראובן Ruby
to do חליצה chalitzah just... I mean, we've had these cases
of...
yeah, right, and she'd be אסורה asura to the כהן kohen and
whatever. It's crazy, I'm, you know, because it's like, first of all,
it's just so severe and what did she do wrong? But number
two, as you're saying, it's like and what is it that you're
supposed to do to prevent this from happening? Like at least in
the first case you can say, have somebody who knows how to
do a גט get, supervise everything and at least you can prevent
the cases. But really you're supposed to, I mean... so yeah, let's
read one more case, okay? Let's finish
the משנה. הכונס את יבמתו hakones et yevamto והלכה צרתה. vehalcha tzarata.
Now how about this case? A guy did ייבום, yibbum, okay? He
had two sister-in-laws, he did ייבום yibbum with
one, so the co-wife went ונישאת לאחר. veniseit leachair. So if you
do ייבום yibbum with one of the wives, the other wives are
free to get remarried, they don't need חליצה. chalitzah. So the co-wife
went and got married to another guy, right? Exactly.
So ונמצאת זו שהיא אילונית. venimtzeit zu shehi aylonit. And it turns
out that the wife that was part of the, that did ייבום,
yibbum, she actually was an אילונית. aylonit. She turned out retroactively she
was never the wife. So she was never the wife, ייבום yibbum
was never done, so the co-wife still required ייבום yibbum or
חליצה. chalitzah. So תצא מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה. teitzei mizeh
umizeh vechol hadrachim ha’elu bah. She has to suffer all the consequences.
כתב סופר גט לאיש ושובר לאישה. katav sofer get la’ish veshovar la’ishah.
Now what if a סופר sofer basically wrote the גט get. for
the man and for the woman he wrote a שובר, shovar, a
receipt? I have received, you know, the payment of my כתובה. ketubah.
And he was going to give it to the woman, so once
she was paid her כתובה ketubah he would give it to the
husband, okay? וטעה ונתן גט לאישה ושובר לאיש. veta’ah venatan get la’ishah
veshovar la’ish. He delivered the wrong documents. Maybe both of them were
illiterate? Okay. Of course you would imagine a גט get would be
a little bit longer than whatever. Anyway, okay. ונתנו זה לזה. venatnu
zeh lazeh. And they gave each other the document. He gave her
the thing he thought was a גט get which was a receipt,
and then he paid her the כתובה ketubah and then she gave
him the thing she thought was a receipt which was a גט.
get So she’s divorced?
Exactly. Okay, so there she really is married to the first guy
still. Okay. ולאחר זמן הרי הגט יוצא מיד האיש והשובר מיד האישה.
v’le’achar zman harei haget yotzei miyad ha’ish vehashovar miyad ha’ishah. Then later
somebody says, oh, could I look at your documents? What are you
doing with a גט? get You were supposed to give the גט
get, to her. What is this, a receipt? So all of a
sudden they realize the mistake. So what’s the הלכה? halacha? תצא מזה
ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה. teitzei mizeh umizeh vechol hadrachim ha’elu bah.
So again, she suffers all the consequences. She got remarried on the
basis, turns out that she wasn’t actually divorced. So she essentially is
now ממש mamash married to the first guy still. All the consequences
because she’s now, but it looks like she’s married to the second
guy. So she’s married to two guys, all the consequences. רבי אליעזר
אומר אם לאלתר יצא אין זה גט. Rabbi Eliezer omer im l’altar
yatza ein zeh get. If you took the documents immediately, then you’re
right.
He said what?
If you looked at the documents immediately, then you’re right. Then it
wasn't a good גט Get, and whatever consequences are consequences. ואם לאחר
זמן יצא. v’im l’achar zman yatza. If however a year after it
was given you asked, could I see the document? And you see
it was the wrong one. So then he says, לא כל הימנו
מן הראשון לאבד זכותו של שני. lo kol heimenu min harishon l’abeid
zchuto shel sheni. You’re the first husband. You’re saying to the wife,
you know what, could I check your גט Get for a minute?
And then, you know, she’s already married to the second guy, and
then she produces this receipt. He says, ah, sorry, looks like I
never gave you the גט, Get you gotta get divorced from the
guy number two. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, I’m sorry, buddy.
Like, who knows what happened from the time a year ago when
you gave it to now? And you don't have the right, the
ability, if you looked at the documents later, how do you know
it's the same document? Maybe you snuck in, you swapped the documents,
who the heck knows what? Okay. So therefore, if the documents right
away are obviously wrong, they're wrong. But if later you look at
them, I'm not going to believe that those were the same documents
that were given. You can't go ahead and now make problems for
her with her second husband. Okay, so that's like a different type
of an issue of being clarifying what really happened, yeah? ואחר
זמן. v'achar zman. Well the גמרא's going to ask how much לאחר
זמן l'achar zman is לאחר זמן. l'achar zman. Good, yeah.
Yeah, I have a methodological question, the same general סתם משנה stam
Mishnah is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Does that mean that there is
a possibility to always treat סתם משנה stam Mishnah as a דעת
יחיד da’at yachid if we want to narrow its applicability?
Yeah, meaning it is true, on the one hand סתם משנה stam
Mishnah is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, on the other hand... Because it's
made סתם *stam*, it's presumed that רבי *Rebbi* gave it the authority.
Yes, but if the גמרא *Gemara* wants to, the גמרא *Gemara* can.
Yes, that methodological possibility. That is true. And I mean we're going
to see תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, the גמרא *Gemara* never
is clear explicit that we don't rule like this משנה *Mishnah*, but
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* makes a point that we don't. Okay, speaking of
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, and although it is late, I'll just read one
line from תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*. Look at תוספות Tosafot ושמי ושמי רב
Rav *Tosafos u-shemi u-shemi Rav*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says אמר Amar, רבינו
יצחק *Amar Rabbeinu Yitzchak*, דהיינו דוקא עיר שדרים בה *de-haynu davka ir
she-darim bah*. The idea that they have to have the names that
they have to have the names in the גט Get *get* and
they have to be the correct names is the current city where
the person is living. אבל עיר שנולד בה *Aval ir she-nolad bah*,
the city of origin, אפילו שינה כשר *afillu shina kasher*, even if
you got it wrong it's כשר *kasher*, כיון שאין צריך לכותבו כלל
*keivan she-ein tzarich le-kotvo klal* because you really aren't obligated to write
a city of origin. והקדמונים נהגו לכותבו *Ve-ha-kadmonim nahagu le-kotvo*,
תוספות Tosfot, *Tosafos*'s giving you a little history. It's true it's an
old practice to write city of origin. Why is that? I don't
think we do. Anyway, משום שמא יהיה ערר שיש שם יוסף בן
שמעון אחר יהיה שמו ושם עירו מקום לידה *mishum shema yihiyeh arar
she-yesh sham Yosef ben Shimon acher yihiyeh shemo ve-shem iro mekom leida*,
right? Very hard you know when you just have father's name, how
do you know there might be ten guys with the same name?
So you also put in city of origin so it makes it
clear like we would call it putting in שם משפחה *shem mishpacha*,
like that is very helpful at identifying a family name. But they
would put in city of origin to help identify, but it wasn't
required.
So that became family names sometimes.
Sometimes it did become family name, right, exactly. So a good point.
So if so therefore תוספות Tosfot *Tosafos* says since it wasn't required
and then if it got therefore
now you could have said it's not required but if you did
it and got it wrong that's worse than not having it at
all. But תוספות Tosfot *Tosafos*, as we're going to see for practical
reasons, is saying yes we did in certain saying we're not going
to say that. דחזינן דכמה פעמים כותבים מקום לידה פי הבעל או
האשה אם שינה פסול pasul לא היה נכון לכתבו *De-chazinan de-kama pe'amim
kotvim mekom leida pi ha-ba'al o ha-isha im shina pasul lo haya
nachon le-kotvo*. This is Michael, the question you're asking. We ask the
husband where were you born and we just believe him and we
write it down. Now תוספות Tosfot *Tosafos* says this is proof that
it can't be פסול pasul בדיעבד *pasul be-di'avad* if you got it
wrong. Because if it was פסול pasul? בדיעבד *pasul be-di'avad* if you
got it wrong then I would ask for some proof, I wouldn't
just take him on his word. Okay? So תוספות Tosfot *Tosafos* develops
this whole idea that because it's not necessary, even if you do
it and get it wrong it's not פסול *pasul*.
Would they have to ask for proof
did he carry his birth certificate? Well so that's the questions you've
been asking and תוספות Tosfot *Tosafos* gets to that. So but yes
you do need some objective evidence. So then תוספות Tosfot *Tosafos* says
if you look at the bottom, you know תוספות Tosfot *Tosafos* says
like this, ומעשה באחד *u-ma'aseh be-echad*. It's line starts with the word
באחד *be-echad* about eight lines before תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* is over. ומעשה
באחד ששינה בגט מקום לידתו *U-ma'aseh be-echad she-shina be-get mekom leidato*, that
he gave the wrong name of his birth origin in the גט
Get *get*. והכשירו ר"י *Ve-hishiro Ri*. And Rabbeinu Yitzchak who started this
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* right said okay we got the name of the
origin wrong it's still a כשר *kasher* גט Get *get*. Okay? So
והרבה פעמים כשלא היה להם ברור מקום הלידה *ve-harbe pe'amim ke-shelo haya
lahem barur mekom ha-leida*, and many times if it was not clear
where the guy was born, I don't know, how does the guy
know where he was born? Like if his family moved when he
was young. היה אומר אל תכתבו כלל *Haya omer al tichtevu klal*.
Okay, don't write the city of origin. Okay? And then and then
goes on it says how about where the guy is right now
where it's being written where the guy is standing right now whichever.
So very interesting a little history that they would write city of
origin and Dov makes an excellent point that that actually very often
became a type of a family name. And but nevertheless you know
to try to save פסולי גיטין gittin. *psulei gittin* saying since it
wasn't necessary getting it wrong doesn't פסול *pasul* it. And תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* has an interesting discussion earlier about that about שם לוואי *shem
livai* as well and about כינויים *kinuyim* and about nicknames etc. If
you didn't have to and you did it and got it wrong
does it make it פסול *pasul*?
The ר"י *Ri* is רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*'s nephew.
The ר"י *Ri* is רבינו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*'s nephew. Okay. מאי מלכות
Malchut, שאינה הוגנת *Mai malchut she-eina hogenet*? Let's look at the גמרא
*Gemara*. Okay what is מאי מלכות Malchut שאינה הוגנת *mai malchut she-eina
hogenet*? What's an improper government? מלכות Malchut הרומים *Malchut ha-romim*, the Romans.
ואמאי קרו לה מלכות Malchut שאינה הוגנת *Ve-amai karu lah malchut she-eina
hogenet*? So why doesn't it just say if you dated by the
Romans? So the גמרא *Gemara* says משום דאין להם כתב ולא לשון
*mishum de-ein lahem ktav ve-lo lashon*. Yeah because they're all you know
they're גנבים *ganavim*. They don't even have their own natural language they
stole their language from the I don't know from the Greeks. It's
not true. I mean the Roman letters...
That's the one thing that they didn't steal from anyone. Right. They
were they they stole everything from everybody but they had their own
Latin alphabet.
The Latin letters was uniquely a Roman thing.
The Latin alphabet and the Latin language were from that part of
Italy.
It's so not true.
That's interesting. So what does the what does the Steinsaltz say anything
to
make sense of that?
What
he possibly means...
The Latins it was the language of the Latins a nation and
country of the city of Rome assimilated incorporated within it. Based on
the Etruscan alphabet with the modifications of Latin but they were all
in the same part of Italy I don't understand.
Anyway and I still go back to my question which is if
the problem is if it's a different מלכות Malchut, *malchut*, excuse me
where the משנה *Mishnah*'s being read it's not a different מלכות *malchut*.
Now maybe the משנה *Mishnah* is saying we don't like the Romans
because they oppress us and that's why it's a מלכות שאינה הוגנת
*malchut she-eina hogenet* but then of course okay but then what are
you supposed to date it? Don't date it by the Romans don't
date it by בניין הבית binyan ha-bayit. *binyan ha-bayit* don't date it
by the Greeks. So how are you? I don't understand. And if
it merely is that it's a different מלכות *malchut* well I mean
does it mean because you're supposed to write
by by your local... Yeah right okay moving on. We don't have
answers.
I don't know yeah. If you were well supposedly we were supposed
to do. Right.
I presumably you are supposed to write Rome.
I don't know.
Anyway going on.
In
Rome what you should do. When in Rome exactly don't do like
Rome. Okay אמר עולא מפני מה תיקנו מלכות בגיטין? mipnei mah tiknu
malchut be-gittin?
Why did they say you're supposed to write it after the reigning
government? משום שלום מלכות mishum shalom malchut to make peace with the
government. You want it now תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion about
does this apply to other שטרות shtarot and he basically says no
it seems it really only applies to גיטין. gittin Other שטרות shtarot
are dated by מנין שטרות minyan shtarot and בית המקדש Beit Ha-Mikdash
and so on and he says because גיטין Gittin are so consequential
about personal status we felt it particularly important to have this sort
of שלום מלכות shalom malchut type of an idea.
So I mean the מלכות cares about these?
That's the way תוספות Tosafot phrased it. No because the גמרא's going
to want to say that they would be more מקפיד makpid in
scenario A than in scenario B.
So the מלכות has like a marriage registry? They just kind of
want to know I guess?
Exactly. Or but no but but they do know but this is
such an important personal status document that they want it to acknowledge
like in the state of New York, like don't you know yes
it's your own little religious thing as well but you know for
these types of things it should be have an official type of
a dating.
Yes or it's the date that everyone knows like here you you
ask for the Hebrew date they're not going to necessarily know. Right.
That's the date that everyone knows. You want people to know when
it was.
Oh that's an interesting point. I mean that's not the שלום מלכות
shalom malchut argument but it's a different argument. It's so consequential that
you want it to be a dating that everybody everybody refers to
and understands the date. That's a very good point. Okay so the
גמרא now says ומשום שלום מלכות תצא והולד ממזר? u-mishum shalom malchut
tetzei ve-ha-vlad mamzer? So just to make for that reason we're going
to have this big consequence? So the גמרא says אין in yes
רבי מאיר לטעמיה Rabbi Meir le-ta'ameih דאמר רבי מאיר אמר המנונא משמיה
דעולא אמר היה רבי מאיר. de-amar Rabbi Meir amar Hamnuna mishmeih de-Ulla
amar hayah Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir used to say כל המשנה מהמטבע
שטבעו חכמים בגיטין הולד ממזר. kol ha-meshaneh me-ha-matbeia she-tavu chachamim be-gittin ha-vlad
mamzer. Or as רש"י Rashi, says, רש"י, Rashi you see now I'm
calling you רש"י, Rashi as Michael said before, the side has the
גירסא girsa that says אלא אלא אלא תוציא
והולד ממזר. ella ella ella totzi ve-ha-vlad mamzer. Okay anyway okay so
if you take a look anyway תוספות Tosafot throws in there תוספות
Tosafot. I mentioned מפני מה תיקנו mipnei mah tiknu the little end
of that תוספות Tosafot. אמר ר"י דדווקא בגיטין יש לחוש לשלום מלכות
שמקפידין לפי שהוא דבר גדול שמפרידין איש מאשתו. amar Ri de-davka be-gittin
yesh lachosh le-shalom malchut she-makpidin lefi she-hu davar gadol she-mafridin ish me-ishto.
Okay so let's see the rest of this מלכות לשם מלכות יוון
le-shem malchut Yavan וצריכא. u-tzricha. It has to tell me this because
you already told me a presumably a different government why mention the
Greeks? דאי אשמעינן מלכות שאינה הוגנת de-i ashme'inan malchut she-eina hogenet if
you had just said you named it after Rome משום דמליכא mishum
de-malicha because they're a current מלכות their current you know
sovereign nation and therefore you're giving
recognition it's like cheating on their government you know cheating on your
husband cheating on your government. So you're giving recognition to an existing
other nation another מלכות. Okay אבל מלכות מדי ומלכות יוון aval malchut
Madai u-malchut Yavan you name it after some ancient and dead nation
מה דהוה הוה mah de-havah havah so maybe it's not a שלום
מלכות shalom malchut, idea. Yes you know it's not as bad you
know you should have given this מלכות recognition but it's not like
you were prioritizing another a competitor. These are long and dead kingdoms.
Okay ואי אשמעינן מלכות מדי ומלכות יוון ve-i ashme'inan malchut Madai u-malchut
Yavan if you said that even that was a problem even though
they're long and
dead משום דמלכותא הוו mishum de-malchuta havu because at least they were
kingdoms. So they might be dead but you're still saying oh well
you know the ancient great you know
Median or the Greeks like it's still it פוגע pogei'a in my
כבוד. kavod. Like they're the great governments and who am I? So
anyway they're the great מלכות. Okay אבל בניין הבית aval binyan ha-bayit
but maybe you would think that if you know you named it
after something that was not a competitor to my authority. It was
because of your own religious sensibilities you named it after the בניין
הבית. I might think מה דהוה הוה. mah de-havah havah. Fine you
want to name it after your ancient בית המקדש? I don't feel
threatened by that. So no even that's not good. ואי אשמעינן בניין
הבית ve-i ashme'inan binyan ha-bayit if you said that דאמרי קא מדכרי
שבחייהו de-amri ka madcharei shivcheihu that's still a sense of a competition.
Oh we used to be great and sovereign so that's also I'm
offended by your my sense of authority you know my authority. אבל
חורבן הבית aval churban ha-bayit but if you're going to name it
after the destruction of the בית המקדש דצערא הוא de-tza'ara hu that
that actually is just your mourning something and you're not I'm not
feeling threatened at all. You're not trying to I mean you know
in some little way you're trying to harken to your to your
great ancient times but very indirectly you're just mourning it. I would
feel okay I'm not מקפיד makpid I'm not threatened. אימא לא וצריכא.
eima lo u-tzricha. Even that's a שלום מלכות shalom malchut. idea. So
it frames it all as an issue about the הקפדה hakpada of
the government. So given that I want to just jump for a
second I mean to
the תוספות let's just flip the page for one quick second תוספות
on פ"ז ע"ב peh-zayin amud bet just jump ahead if you take
a look תוספות says
I'm not going to go through this whole תוספות, but תוספות asks
the question about how do we give our current documents. Okay, and
so he says
והרב רב יוסף. V'HaRav Rav Yosef. It's like the middle of that
long column. The line starts with the word הרבה. Harbe. Do people
see the line הרבה Harbe like in the middle of that column?
Like it's two, three lines under the parentheses of בבא בתרא. Bava
Batra. Okay. So he says והרב רב יוסף פירש V'HaRav Rav Yosef
peireish דעכשיו אין המלכות מקפדת. de'achshav ein hamalchut makpedet. Now the government
doesn't care how we date things. ולהכי לא כתבינן לשנות מלכים. Ulehachi
lo katvinan lishnot melachim. And therefore we don't write it anymore for
the מלכים. melachim. Okay. תדע, Teda, he says, דרבי מאיר מודה דכתבו
deRabbi Meir modeh dechtavo or whatever. Okay. Da da da. And then
he goes to the גמרא that we haven't read yet. Right.
Okay. And then he says, okay, do you see the line go
down to like a third, like 10 lines before the lines get
wide, שמותר. shemutar. He says like this, he
says וכל שכן השתא
שמותר לכתוב לבריאת עולם V'chol sheken hashta shemutar lichtov livriat olam דלא
זילא בה מילתא כלל delo zila bah milta klal דלא מסתקני בהא.
delo mistaknei beha. Okay. וקיימא לן כחכמים V'kayma lan k'Chachamim and we
don't hold like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir etc. So תוספות deals with
the fact that we date it לבריאת עולם livriat olam and we
assume that nowadays the government doesn't care if we name things לבריאת
עולם, livriat olam, they're not threatened or whatever. Yes. So
he's eliminating, well, the מלכות problem. Now there are other problems as
well. That's going to be the other question of do we פסקן
pasken רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, do we פסקן pasken חכמים. Chachamim. But
the argument he's making right here is is that in scenarios where
there isn't, based on our גמרא, that maybe this case it wouldn't
be a שלום מלכות, shalom malchut this case it wouldn't be a
שלום מלכות. shalom malchut, Now the question is what's the end of
the גמרא? The end of the גמרא is doesn't matter if there
is a שלום מלכות shalom malchut or not, it's always פסול when
you give it a wrong date. That's a very reasonable conclusion. תוספות
concludes no, in scenarios where we can say there's no issue of
שלום מלכות, it's the dating issue is not going to be a
problem. And that's even if you would פסקן pasken our משנה, even
according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, if it's not a שלום מלכות
issue, the dating is not a problem. Okay, so that's point number
one, that's how we do בריאת עולם. briat olam. Yes, Charlie.
When did we start using the current?
I don't know. Okay. Now moving on in the גמרא. היה במזרח
וכתב במערב. Haya bamizrach vechatav bama'arav. He was in the east and
wrote for the west.
So the גמרא says like this. מאן? Man? Who was in the
east and he wrote for the west? אילימא בעל? Ilima ba'al? If
it means the husband? It means like he, he, the husband comes
from East Berlin and he wrote that he came from West Berlin.
So היינו שינוי שמו ושמה שמו ושם עירו. hainu shinui shemo v'shma
shemo v'shem iro. That's later in the משנה. You gave him a
wrong location. Okay. The, you know, the city he's from. אלא לאו
סופר? Ela lav sofer? It means where it's being written. Right? The,
there were a lot of names, you know,
in the גט. First you write like a כתובה, ketubah, you know,
where you write like, you know,
בשני בשבת besheni beshabat blah blah blah blah blah, you know, במנין
שאנו מונים כאן, beminyan she'anu monim kan, whatever, you know, whatever we
said, you know, Riverdale, New York, we're not in Riverdale, you probably
do New York because you do the city and this is just
a borough. New York, New York. Okay, anyway, fine. So that's where
the סופר sofer is. Where is the גט being written? Okay? Then
you write איך פלוני בר פלוני דממסטא פלוני, eich ploni bar ploni
d'mimasta ploni, right? And you give his name and his father's name
and his city. אמר, you know, and whatever and he said, you
know, and he whatever to this woman from this city. Okay? So
there are three cities mentioned: where the גט is being written, where
the man is from, where the woman is from.
So that's the גמרא about where the גט is being written. What?
And who does he actually care?
Right, so that's a good question. Like really, who does care where
the גט is being written? And so that's why again it's sort
of like it's a even a even a smaller trivial issue. And
תוספות has a huge discussion about this issue about what happens if
I am here writing a כתובה, ketubah, right? I go ahead and
I give it to, you know, my friend the artist to do
a beautiful paper cut כתובה. ketubah. And there it is. And it
is a year before the wedding and she's over in Kansas somewhere
doing it and she's writing though New York, New York. So she's
writing the place that she's not in. Okay, now there although you
could say that doesn't matter, it matters like when it's signed not
when it's written. Okay. But תוספות still deals with the issue of,
I don't know, what happens if it's signed before the wedding? And
then you use it at the wedding. So it's not going to
be the place that it's being used for, let's say it's postdated
for the wedding. And the place, and so at the, at the
date that it reflects is where it was being used on that
date, you know, in New York, New York. That's where the wedding
took place, but that wasn't where it was written and where it
was signed. So תוספות gets into all of that discussion. But yes,
that is obviously less, we don't real, but the reason I'm saying
this is at some level we don't really care where the heck
the סופר sofer was. But what we do care about is where
did this event take place. So the date in the כתובה ketubah
is more intended to reflect where the event was taking place. But
what happens if, you know, the סופר sofer wrote it and he's
not there at the moment of the event? And that's what תוספות
deals with. Okay? But גיטין too. Right? Why? We don't care where
the סופר sofer was if it took place before. The purpose of
the name of the location in the גט, the same way the
purpose of the date, is to show where and when it took
place. The only problem is sometimes the date was when it was
a year before it took place because it was written before it
was given. Right? So there's like things so the The basic point
of the place
and the date is to know where and when, but they don't
always synchronize with that. But that's why we do write it. And
here it says that if you wrote the wrong place and again
תוספות deals with the fact that, well, I don't know, let's say
it was signed later, let's say it was the right place where
it was given but the wrong place where the סופר Sofer was.
Anyway, that's what תוספות deals with. Anyway, but that's the
case. והלכתא ספרא, V’hilchta Safra, כדאמר ליה רב לספריה, k’d’amar leh Rav
l’safrei, וכן אמר ליה רב הונא לספריה, v’chein amar leh Rav Huna
l’safrei, רב לספריה, Rav l’safrei, רב said to his סופר Sofer and
רב הונא Rav Huna said to his סופר, Sofer, כי יתביתו בשילי
כתובו בשילי, ki yasvitu b’Shili ktuvu b’Shili, when you're in שילי Shili
and you're writing a גט, write, you know, there, or whatever you're
writing, תוספות discusses other documents as well, here we are in, you
know, in שילי Shili on this date, da-da-da-da-da. ואף על גב דמימסרן
לכו מילי בהיני, V’af al gav d’mimsaran l’chu mili b’Hini, even though
תוספות says this was like a neighboring city, even though the husband
told you write a גט for my wife and all of you
guys were in היני Hini when he told you this, if you're
sitting in שילי Shili when you're writing it, write we are in
שילי Shili such and such occurred, do not write based on where
you got the instruction and where the husband was, write where you
are when you're writing it. וכי יתביתו בהיני כתובו בהיני, V’chi yasvitu
b’Hini ktuvu b’Hini, ואף על גב דמימסרן לכו מילי בשילי, v’af al
gav d’mimsaran l’chu mili b’Shili, and the same in the reverse. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel,
זו דברי רבי מאיר. zu divrei Rabbi Meir. This, all is the
position of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, now רש"י Rashi says this
is going back to the שם מלכות Shem Malchut issue. תוספות says
that this is actually going back to the... well let me see
what תוספות says, you could have said it's going to the שינה
שם העיר, Shina Shem Ha-ir, but hold on, let me just double
check תוספות.
Well let's read a little bit, okay, and then I'll go back
to תוספות. זו דברי רבי מאיר. Zu divrei Rabbi Meir. This is
the position of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. אבל חכמים אומרים אפילו לא
כתב אלא שם סנטר שבעיר הרי זו מגורשת. Aval Chachamim omrim afilu
lo katav ela shem Santar shebe-ir harei zu megureshet. Oh, no, this
clearly is מלכות, I'm sorry I was thinking later. This idea that,
that if you did the wrong מלכות, so we're jumping back to
the מלכות as opposed to the
location. Okay, that the wrong מלכות is פסול and has all these
consequences, that's according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. But the חכמים Chachamim
say אפילו לא כתב אלא שם סנטר שבעיר הרי זו מגורשת. afilu
lo katav ela shem Santar shebe-ir harei zu megureshet. Even if you
wrote it in the name of some type of a local, like,
you know, type of a city
official...
Bill de Blasio,
in the third year of the reign of Mayor de Blasio of
whatever, it works. Now by the way... okay, so ההוא גיטא דהוה
כתיב ביה לשם אסתדרא דבשכר. Hahu gita d’hava ktiv bei l’shem istadra
d’Bashkar. I don't even know how to pronounce it. Anyway, there was
a certain גט that was written in the name of some type
of a governor of בשכר, Bashkar, okay, which was an appointee of
the king. שלחו רב נחמן ורב חסדא לקמיה דרבא. Shalchu Rav Nachman
v’Rav Chisda l’kamei d’Rava. So and it wasn't named in the reign
of the king, but in the reign of the governor. But the
governor was an appointee of the king. So he sent it in
front of רבא. Rava. כי האי גוונא מאי? Ki hai gavna mai?
What's the story, is that like not in the name of the
real king and therefore it's פסול? שלח להו, Shalach lehu, no, בהא
אפילו רבי מאיר מודה. be-ha afilu Rabbi Meir modeh. This even רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir wouldn't have a problem with. מאי טעמא? Mai ta’ama?
מאותה מלכות הוא. me-ota malchut hu. He's an official of the government,
so
you
didn't
give honor to the king, but he
is
an appointed official. ומאי שנא מסנטר שבעיר? U-mai shna mi-Santar shebe-ir?
How's that different from the סנטר Santar which we said actually would
be invalid according to רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? The חכמים Chachamim would
say it's okay but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say it's invalid.
התם זילא ליה מילתא. Hatam zila leh milta. No, there it's, you
know, it's, it's, it's disrespectful to the מלכות because that's not even...
רש"י says he's not an important official at all, maybe he's not
even a government official. הכא שביחא ליה מילתא. Hacha shevicha leh milta.
Here it's a חשוב chashuv governor, the guy they appointed. Okay. Let's
see what this סנטר Santar is then.
רש"י
says he's some like petty little city official. So, okay, you use
the name after like when the postman, you know, the reign of
the postman since he's the governor, whatever, you know, come on, that's
a
disgrace. אמר רב אבא אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar Rav Abba
amar Rav Huna amar Rav, זו דברי רבי מאיר. zu divrei Rabbi
Meir. These are
the words of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. אבל חכמים אומרים הולד כשר. Aval Chachamim omrim
ha-vlad kasher.
This idea that when you make a mistake... now there's one question
what defines a mistake, what defines a wrong מלכות, but there's another
question what's the consequence of the mistake. So this idea in the
משנה that if you get it wrong it has all of these
terrible consequences, that's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, like we said before. אבל
חכמים אומרים הולד כשר. Aval Chachamim omrim ha-vlad kasher. Okay,
but that's the first half of the משנה.
ומודים חכמים לרבי מאיר,
U-modim Chachamim l’Rabbi Meir, and maybe also שינה שם העיר shina shem
ha-ir where the גט was written, okay. But ומודים חכמים לרבי מאיר
שאם שינה שמו ושמה שם עירו ושם עירה שהולד ממזר. u-modim Chachamim
l’Rabbi Meir she-im shina shmo u-shmah shem iro v’shem irah she-havlad mamzer.
That
if you do actually change the name of the man or the
woman or their location, that's much more central. Well, but again, depends,
it might not be that it's בטל דאורייתא batel d'Oraita if it's
a small mistake and sometimes it's a secondary type of a name
or whatever. So it's not so פשוט pashut that it's בטל דאורייתא,
batel d'Oraita, but it is much more central to the גט and
therefore ולד ממזר. vlad mamzer. אמר רב אשי אף אנן נמי תנינא,
Amar Rav Ashi af anan nami tanina, that's clear in the משנה
because the משנה says, שינה שמו ושמה שם עירו ושם עירה תצא
מזה ומזה וכל הדרכים האלו בה. shina shemo u'shemah sheim iro u'sheim
irah teizei mizeh u'mizeh v'chol hadrachim ha'elu bah. So מאן תנא לה?
man tana lah? So who is telling this second half of the
משנה about שינה שמו ושמה? shina shemo u'shemah? אילימא Ileima רבי מאיר,
Rebbi Meir, if it was רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, לירבין ולתנינהו. lirvin
v'lisneinhu. Why not do all, why not list all the cases together?
Why did the משנה list the case of changing their names or
changing their locations as a separate clause, you know, as a separate
statement? Just give the whole list of all the problems. The fact
that it says here are all the consequences, oh, and by the
way here's another problem, so that's telling you שמע מינה רבנן, shma
mina Rabbanan, that that issue of שם עירו ושם עירה sheim iro
u'sheim irah is a problem even according to the rabbis, שמע מינה.
shma mina. So because of this you could imagine when they write
a גט how crazy they go about the names and the names
of the locations because here we're saying even according to the חכמים
chachamim the consequences could be disastrous. Okay, so that's we will end
on that up on that note.